Finding Aid for Academic Women’s Caucus (University of Michigan) records, 1970-2008
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Academic Women’s Caucus (University of Michigan) records 1970-2008, 1975-1998
University of Michigan. Academic Women’s Caucus.
4 linear feet
91459 Bimu B29 2
Organization of women faculty members established to exchange information about their status as faculty women and to investigate and resolve issues of special concern. records include history, awards files, correspondence, minutes, topical files, photographs, and videotapes.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group (Donor no. 7889 ) was transferred, beginning in 1991.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The record group is open without restriction.
The Academic Women's Caucus (AWC) was officially formed in 1975 as an outgrowth of the Commission for Women, a unit of the Affirmative Action Office. The idea for the AWC was developed at a brown-bag lunch meeting which included Ann Larimore, Jean Cobb, Zelda Gamson, Harriet Mills, and Eunice Burns, all faculty and staff members of the University of Michigan. They decided to work with the Women's Commission Committee which was also interested in organizing a women's academic group. The group was first formed as the Academic Women's Committee of the Commission for Women and later was called the Faculty Women's Committee. In the summer of 1975, it took its present name, the Academic Women's Caucus.
The purpose of the group, as described in an AWC pamphlet, is "...to develop an inclusive organization of all women faculty members of the Ann Arbor, Dearborn, and Flint campuses of The University of Michigan which will serve as a forum for the exchange of information about the status of faculty women at the University and as a focus for action necessary to the investigation and resolution of their special concerns. The history of the AWC and the equality movement of women faculty at the University is documented in the video Striving Toward Equity at the University of Michigan: 25 Years of the Academic Women's Caucus 1975-2000. The video was produced by member Ruth Barnard from 1999 to 2000 and reconstructs, through interviews, photographs and narration, the difficulties and discrimination faced by women faculty at the University.
"Via task forces and the initiative of individual members, the AWC has researched and testified in a variety of salary and equity surveys and cases at The University of Michigan. It has made presentations to the Board of Regents, and is consulted regularly by the Affirmative Action Office and top University administrators. Orientation sessions for new faculty women were an early and on-going feature of the Caucus. The continued monitoring and publicizing of data about the status of women faculty, primary researchers, librarians and curators was and remains a high priority. Women interested in academic administration have been identified and nominated for training workshops such as the one at Bryn Mawr each summer. The Caucus also regularly nominates women candidates for various awards and administrative positions.
"A new co-chair is selected each year and usually serves for two years, thus providing continuity for the group. Recently a steering committee was formed to help plan for the entire group, and as another continuity mechanism. This group is composed of several past chairs, current co-chairs, task force conveyors, and others interested in serving. Sub-committees and short-term task forces allow members to work on behalf of the caucus for the amount and duration of effort their schedules permit. The Affirmative Action Office of the University provides office support and other services to facilitate the work of the AWC." (See Box 1, folder: History, Awards Ceremony Program)
Additional information about the University of Michigan Academic Women's Caucus can be found on their website. Information includes meeting minutes, upcoming events, a history of the organization and of the Sarah Goddard Power award, links to other university and nationwide organizations devoted to women and women faculty members, and contact information. The website is located at http://sitemaker.umich.edu/awc/home (as of 11/08/2006).
The records of the Academic Women's Caucus (AWC) provide an almost complete history of the AWC from its origins to the present, although the materials documenting the years 1972-1974 are not particularly strong. Many of the early records are from the co-chair Aline Soules. The records do provide valuable documentation of the general concerns of women faculty members at a major research university.
The records of the AWC consist of eight series: History, Awards, Correspondence, Minutes, Topical, Photographs, Audio-Visual Material, and Striving Towards Equality.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Academic Women's Caucus.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; College teachers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women college teachers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Audio-Visual Materials:
University of Michigan. Academic Women's Caucus.; Vainstein, Rose, 1920-; College teachers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women college teachers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Women's rights--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Affirmative action programs--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Contributors:
Barnard, Ruth M.; Bollinger, Lee C., 1946-; Campbell, Jean.; Cantor, Nancy.; Carpenter, Eugenia S.; Douvan, Elizabeth Ann Malcolm, 1926-; Duderstadt, James J., 1942-; Duell, Elizabeth.; Dumas, Rhetaugh.; Gage, Lois Waite.; Goldenberg, Edie N.; Hollenshead, Carol.; Hollingsworth, Peggie J.; Kaplan, Wilfred, 1915-; King, Jean.; Larimore, Ann E.; Marcelo, Cynthia.; Mills, Harriet C.; Nordby, Virginia.; Rasmussen, Susan.; Reed, Beth Glover.; Sarri, Rosemary C.; Soules, Aline.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Videotapes.; Sound recordings.
- History
  The series History, 1974-1994 (0.1 linear ft.), consists of a 1974 handwritten chronology of the AWC, a memo concerning the "Proposed Organizational Structure of Academic Women Committee and Program Format," a summary of meeting topics from 1976 to 1980, notes on the issues and accomplishments of the AWC, a listing of women involved in the group, and a pamphlet issued by the AWC which sets forth the goals of the organization and a list of the co-chairs from 1975 to 1985.
  - General 1974-1994, 1 folder (Box 1)
- Awards 1971-1998
  The series Awards, 1971-1998 (0.9 linear ft.), contains materials documenting the annual awards sponsored by the AWC. Prior to 1988 these awards were called the Academic Women's Caucus Awards, but in 1988 the name was changed to the Sarah Goddard Power Awards in memory of Regent Sarah Goddard Power. There is some correspondence relating to the awards, lists of nominees, and other awards ceremony materials including the typescripts of the 1987 and 1988 awards ceremony presentations. Materials relating to the AWC Awards can also be found in the Correspondence series. There are seven folders containing the nomination forms submitted to the AWC awards committee. They provide a valuable resource for the study of outstanding women and men at the university. Each nomination form contains an extensive resume of the individual nominated for the award. This series also contains materials relating to the Alumnae Athena Awards, the American Association of University Women Awards, the Josephine Nevins Keal Fellowship, and the Bunting Fellowship Program. While the AWC is not the funding organization of these awards and fellowships, it nominates women for them.
  - Academic Women's Caucus / Sarah Goddard Power Awards (see also photographs for 1987-1989)
    - Awards Nomination Forms
      - 1986-1990, 5 folders (Box 1)
      - 1995 (Box 1)
      - 1998 (Box 1)
      - 2001 (Box 1)
      - 2003 (Box 1)
      - 2004 (Box 1)
      - 2005 (Box 1)
      - 2006 (Box 1)
      - 2008 (Box 1)
    - General
      - 1986-1987 (Box 1)
      - 1988, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - 1989-2000 (photographs of Sarah Goddard Power Award recipients), 12 folders (Box 1)
    - Procedures and Nominees 1984-1992 (Box 2)
  - Alumnae Athena Awards/Interview Transcript 1971-1980 (Box 2)
  - American Association of University Women (AAUW) 1977-1982 (Box 2)
  - Josephine Nevins Keal Fellowship and the Bunting Fellowship Program 1978-1980 (Box 2)
- Correspondence 1972-1998
  Correspondence, 1972-1998 (0.4 linear ft.), the third series, contains correspondence as well as other supporting materials arranged chronologically from 1972 to 1996; this series is especially strong for the years 1977 to 1987 and 1991 to 1992. Although there is not a great deal of material from the early years of the caucus, there are records relating to the formation of the organization in the folders for the years 1972-1975. (Additional materials on the formation of the AWC can be found in both the Minutes series and the Topical series.) The series is useful for studying the general duties and concerns of the AWC, as well as the annual awards it distributes, the activities of its different committees, and the professional and economic status of women at the university. Also included are e-mail printouts, from 1991-1994 and 1996-1998.
  - General
    - undated (Box 2)
    - 1972-1977 (Box 2)
    - 1978-1981 (Box 2)
    - 1982-1983 (Box 2)
    - 1984 (Box 2)
    - 1985 (Box 2)
    - 1986 (Box 2)
    - 1987 (Box 2)
    - 1988-1990 (Box 2)
    - 1991-1996 (Box 2)
  - E-mail
    - 1991-1994, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - 1996 (Box 2)
    - 1997-1998 (Box 2)
- Minutes 1974-1999
  The series Minutes, 1974-1999 (0.3 linear ft.), contains the minutes for the various committees of the AWC. There are many committees that are represented in the series. Throughout the tenure of the AWC, new committees have been formed and old committees have been eliminated according to the AWC's perspective on the changing roles and needs of women at the University of Michigan. The minutes have been arranged chronologically, but are not separated by committee because the functions of different committees often overlap or relate to each other. There are three main groups of minutes: Steering Committee minutes, AWC Meeting minutes, and AWC Awards Committee Meeting minutes. In most cases various reports from other committees are included in the Steering Committee Meeting minutes. In addition there are some minutes of meetings between individuals, and scattered minutes of University of Michigan organizations in which the AWC played an active role, such as The Women's Commission and the Affirmative Action Office. Where typed minutes were not available, handwritten copies were retained. Minutes for the current academic year can be found on the organizations website.
  - undated (Box 2)
  - 1974-1975 (includes some Commission for Women material) (Box 2)
  - 1976-1984 (scattered dates) (Box 2)
  - 1984-1985 (Box 2)
  - 1985-1986 (Box 2)
  - 1986-1987 (Box 2)
  - 1987-1988 (Box 2)
  - 1989-1999 (scattered dates) (Box 2)
  - 1999-2001 (Box 2)
    (background)
- Topical Files 1970-1999
  The Topical series, 1970-1998 (1.0 linear ft.), is arranged alphabetically and consists mainly of materials relating to the different committees of, and studies undertaken by, the AWC. Of special interest are the Task Force on Primary Research which investigated many different aspects of research at the University of Michigan, especially the existence of gender bias; two reports to the Regents of the University (January 17 and March 14, 1985) in which the AWC presented a summary of their activities and an update on the Task Force on Primary Research study that had been issued in 1983; the Women's Initiative Group (WING), an organization that is interested in developing a closer community of women at the University of Michigan (one project they were especially interested in was a women's center on campus); and the Bryn Mawr and Higher Education Resource Services (HERS) Summer Institute for Women in Higher Education Program in which a tenured faculty woman from the University of Michigan was sponsored for a summer internship. In addition, "Rackham and Women" and "Women's' Platform (Women from the School of Natural Resources)" are two reports which reflect the relationships of women faculty and students at the university.
  - Advancement and Promotion at the University of Michigan 1979-1989 (Box 2)
  - Ad Hoc Committee on Hiring and Retention of Women Faculty Members in the Medical School 1990 (Box 2)
  - Bryn Mawr and Higher Education Resource Services Summer Institute for Women in Higher Education (HERS) Program 1978-1980 (Box 2)
  - Budget 1989-1991 (Box 2)
  - Child Care/Dependent Care 1988-1990 (Box 2)
  - Co-chair 1985, 1991 (Box 2)
  - Committees 1985-1991 (Box 2)
  - Equity Study 1983 (Box 2)
  - FOCUS on Equal Employment for Women 1970 (Box 2)
  - Interview Transcripts, 3 folders (Box 2)
    (includes 7 3.5" Macintosh computer disks which contain the transcripts)
  - Math Club Flyer Incident 1980 (Box 2)
  - The Medium is the Message (The "Fleming Follow") 1972 (Box 2)
  - Meetings 1987-1992 (Box 2)
  - Membership List 1990-1991 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Agenda for Women 1994-1995 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous 1984-1996 (Box 3)
  - Orientation Folder for New Academic Women 1983-1992 (Box 3)
  - President's Advisory Commission on Women's Issues 1989-1991 (Box 3)
  - PROBE into the Status of Women at the University 1970 (PROBE memo no. 2) (Box 3)
  - Program Flyers 1990-1998 (Box 3)
  - Programs Summaries 1988-1990 (Box 3)
  - Rackham and Women 1972 (Box 3)
  - Report to the Regents 1985 (Box 3)
  - Research Productivity ("Women, Men, Race, and the Climate for Research Productivity at the University of Michigan," 1991) (Box 3)
  - Retirement 1990-1991 (Box 3)
  - Salary Equity Report 1983 (Box 3)
  - Seminar with Non-Academic Women 1972 (Box 3)
  - Survey (Box 3)
  - Task Force on Alcohol and other Drugs 1991 (Box 3)
  - Task Force on Women Faculty Reform Coalition 1971 (Box 3)
  - Task Force on Primary Research
    - General 1972-1983 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence 1978-1983 (Box 3)
    - Reports 1979-1983 (Box 3)
    - Salaries and Age Structure 1981-1983 (Box 3)
    - Schools and Colleges
      - Architecture and Urban Planning 1983 (Box 3)
      - School of Art 1983 (Box 3)
      - Business Administration 1983 (Box 3)
      - School of Dentistry 1974, 1983 (Box 3)
      - School of Education 1983 (Box 3)
      - College of Engineering 1983 (Box 3)
      - Institute for Social Research 1979, 1983 (Box 3)
      - Institute of Science and Technology 1983 (Box 3)
      - Law School 1983 (Box 3)
      - Library Science 1983 (Box 3)
      - LS&A 1983 (Box 3)
      - Medical School 1983 (Box 3)
      - Mental Health Research Institute (MHRI) 1983 (Box 3)
      - School of Music 1983 (Box 3)
      - School of Natural Resources 1983 (Box 3)
      - School of Nursing 1983 (Box 3)
      - College of Pharmacy 1983 (Box 3)
      - School of Public Health 1983 (Box 3)
      - School of Social Work 1983 (Box 3)
  - University Governance--Committee Distribution Study 1976-1977 (Box 3)
  - University of Michigan Capital Campaign 1978-1984 (Box 3)
  - University of Michigan Honorary Degrees and Fellowships 1975-1980 (Box 3)
  - Vainstein, Rose (Rose Vainstein Day) 1980 (see also Photographs) (Box 3)
  - Women 1985-1991 (Box 3)
  - Women Graduate Students ("A View of the Status of Women as Graduate Students: A Perspective from Rackham," by Susan Lipschultz, 1992) (Box 3)
  - Women's Initiative Group (WING)
    - General 1987 (Box 3)
    - Recruitment and Retention of Women Faculty 1988 (Box 3)
  - Women's Platform (Women from School of Natural Resources) 1973 (Box 3)
  - Women's Planning Retreat 1986 (Box 3)
- Photographs 1975-2000
  The Photographs, 1975-2000 series (0.2 linear ft.), consists of photographs from the awards ceremonies from 1987 to 1989 (black and white images and proof sheets), portraits of past Sarah Goddard Power award winners, portraits of past organization co-chairs, and a photograph of Rose Vainstein from Rose Vainstein Day in 1980. Vainstein was highly active in the AWC during its early years.
  - Academic Women's Caucus/Sarah Goddard Power Award Ceremonies 1987-1989 (Box 3)
  - Vainstein, Rose (Rose Vainstein Day) 1980 (Box 3)
  - AWC/Sarah Goddard Power Award Recipients 1984-1999 (Box 3)
  - AWC Co-Chairs 1975-2000 (Box 3)
- Audio-Visual Material
  The Audio-visual Material Series consists of audiotapes (1987 and 1988) and videotapes (1998 and 2004) of the AWC's Sarah Goddard Power ceremony.
  - Audiotapes
    - Awards Reception January 29, 1987, 1/4 inch reel to reel tape, 3.75 IPS (Box 3)
    - Awards Reception 1988, Audio cassette tape (Box 3)
  - Videotapes
    - Sarah Goddard Power Awards Ceremony 1998, VHS Videotape (Box 3)
    - 20th Annual Sarah Goddard Power Awards Ceremony 2/18/2004, VHS Videotape (Box 3)
- Striving for Equity
  The series Striving Towards Equality, 1999-2000 (l.0 linear ft.), includes a mixture of documents and video materials relating the project to create a videotape history of the AWC. The video materials consist of the 22 original Betacam SP videotapes used to capture individual interviews of those involved with the formation and work of the Academic Women's Caucus as well as university administrators discussing the impact of the AWC on campus. There is also a VHS copy of the final product Striving Toward Equity at the University of Michigan: 25 Years of the Academic Women's Caucus 1975- 2000. Documents in the series include interview transcripts, signed releases and permissions, and a set of correspondence between Jean King (former AWC member) and Ruth Barnard, the producer of the program, discussing the handling of the HEW complaint of 1970 within the video. The HEW (Health, Education, and Welfare) complaint was the first to challenge sex discrimination practiced by the University and helped to bring about an eye opening investigation into the University's treatment of women faculty. Striving Toward Equity is described as "a historical depiction of the formation of the Academic Women's Caucus, a group whose members lobbied for the hire and promotion of top female administrators, equitable salaries for female faculty and anti-discrimination policies within the University of Michigan." Interviewees include Lee Bollinger, Nancy Cantor, James Duderstadt, Edie Goldenberg, and Jean L. King.
  - Interview Transcripts 1999-2000 (Box 4)
  - Releases and Permissions 1999-2000 (Box 4)
  - Jean L. King Correspondence 2000 (Box 4)
  - Striving Toward Equity at the University of Michigan: 25 Years of the Academic Women's Caucus, 1975-2000, VHS Videotape, 23:50 minutes (Box 4)
  - Striving Toward Equity Videotaped Interviews, 22 videotapes; (Betacam SP
    - Ruth Barnard/Carol Hollenshead December 20, 1999 (Box 4)
    - Lee Bollinger January 6, 2000 (Box 4)
    - Jean Campbell January 3, 2000 (Box 4)
    - Nancy Cantor January 6, 2000 (Box 4)
    - Eugenia Carpenter December 14, 1999 (Box 4)
    - Elizabeth Douvan December 20, 1999 (Box 4)
    - Elizabeth Duell December 14, 1999 (Box 4)
    - Rhetaugh Dumas January 3, 2000 (Box 4)
    - Jim Duderstadt December 20, 1999 (Box 4)
    - Lois Gage December 20, 1999 (Box 4)
    - Edie Goldenberg December 16, 1999 (Box 4)
    - Peggie Hollingsworth December 16, 1999 (Box 4)
    - Wilfred Kaplan January 3, 2000 (Box 4)
    - Jean L. King December 16, 1999 (Box 4)
    - Ann Larimore December 16, 1999 (Box 4)
    - Cynthia Marcelo December 16, 1999 (Box 4)
    - Harriet Mills December 14, 1999 (Box 4)
    - Virginia Nordby December 14, 1999 (Box 4)
    - Sue Rasmussen December 16, 1999 (Box 4)
    - Beth Reed January 3, 2000 (Box 4)
    - Rosemarry Sarri December 14, 1999 (Box 4)
    - Aline Soules December 16, 1999 (Box 4)